Guide to the Benjamin Lincoln Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Benjamin Lincoln Collection
1816-1944
1819-1896
Ms Coll 33
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1
(2 boxes)
Benjamin Lincoln, physician, anatomist, and medical educator, taught anatomy and dissection at the University of Vermont. Papers include family correspondence, two journals of travel to New Orleans and to New Brunswick, circulars, publications in the Burlington Sentinel, ephemera, and photographs, letters, pamphlets, and ephmera by or related to members of the Lincoln family.
Lincoln, Benjamin, 1802-1835
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2011.
Custodial History
Collection is from the family archive, passed down through Edmund Lincoln and Dr. Thomas R. Lincoln, sons of Benjamin Lincoln's brother Thomas Lincoln.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Papers of Benjamin Lincoln, 1823-1835, Countway Library, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA
Biographical / Historical
Benjamin Lincoln, physician, anatomist, and medical educator, was born in Dennsyville, Maine on October 11, 1802, the son of Theodore Lincoln, a judge and founding settler of Dennysville, and Hannah (Mayhew) Lincoln. He graduated from Bowdoin College in 1823. In the period 1825-1827, he spent part of his time in Boston studying medicine under George Cheyne Shattuck and attending selected courses at Harvard Medical School. In 1825-1826, he accompanied an ailing friend, Dr. Henry Little, to New Orleans for Little's health. He received his M.D. from Bowdoin in 1827, after which he began practice in Boston. He was invited to teach the course on anatomy at the University of Vermont in 1828 and was named professor the following year. At the invitation of Nathan Ryno Smith, he taught at the University of Maryland School of Medicine in 1831. Lincoln was a medical reformer who wanted to upgrade standards for admission to medical schools and graduation from them. He became embroiled in an acrimonious controversy over medical education with Dr. Theodore Woodward, Dean of Castleton Medical College in Castleton, Vermont, detailed in two pamphlets Lincoln published in 1833. He published at least four additional pieces on medical education in the Burlington Sentinel in 1834. Long suffering from rheumatism and by 1833 from tuberculosis, Lincoln left Burlington in 1834 to return to his family in Dennysville, where he died on February 26, 1835.
Thomas Lincoln, born in 1812 in Dennsyville, Maine, was the youngest son of Theodore Lincoln. In 1829 he aided his brother Benjamin Lincoln with making anatomical preparations for medical education in Burlington, Vermont. In 1833, he accompanied John James Audubon to Labrador. The Lincoln's sparrow, located and shot on this trip by Lincoln, was named by Audubon for him. He attended the Medical School of Maine at Bowdoin College in 1830 but did not complete an M.D. there. Independently wealthy, Thomas Lincoln oversaw the farm on the family estate in Dennysville until his death in 1883. Among his sons were Dr. Thomas R. Lincoln and Edmund Lincoln.
Scope and Contents
Papers include letters by Benjamin Lincoln to his family, 1819-1834; a journal of his travel to New Orleans and journal of a geological and natural history voyage to New Brunswick; ephemera from his student period at Bowdoin and from Burlington, Vermont; four letters on medical education published in the Burlington Sentinel; copies or drafts of letters and other writings on slavery and other issues by Thomas Lincoln; photographs of the descendents of Theodore Lincoln and of the family home in Dennysville, Maine; pamphlets; and a copy of the Centennial commemoration of the settlement of Dennyville, Maine, 1886, with genealogical information on the Lincoln family. A lengthy letter by Edmund Lincoln, son of Thomas Lincoln, described his travel to Japan in 1896.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: 1. Benjamin Lincoln. 2. Thomas Lincoln and the Lincoln family.
Anatomy, Comparative; Dissection; Medical education -- Vermont; Medicine -- Study and teaching -- United States; Slavery -- Louisiana; Dennysville (Me.) -- History; Japan -- Description and travel; New Brunswick -- Geology; New Orleans (La.) -- Description and travel; Journals; Photographs; Gallup, Joseph A. (Joseph Adams), 1769-1849; Lincoln, Arthur T., 1856-; Lincoln, Benjamin, 1802-1835; Lincoln, Edmund, 1870-; Lincoln, Theodore, 1764-1852; Lincoln, Thomas, 1828-1883; Lincoln family; Little, Henry, 1802-1826; Shattuck, George Cheyne, 1783-1854; Smith, N. R. (Nathan Ryno), 1797-1877; Wells, John Doane, 1799-1830; Woodward, Theodore, 1788-1840; Bowdoin College; Bowdoin College. Medical School; Castleton Medical College (Castleton, Vt.); University of Maryland at Baltimore. School of Medicine; University of Vermont. College of Medicine
- Benjamin Lincoln, 1819-1835; Series I
  - Letters to family, 1819-1821 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    3 items. Letters to his father, Theodore Lincoln, and mother, Hannah (Mayhew) Lincoln from Brunswick, Maine where Lincoln was an undergraduate at Bowdoin College.
  - Letters to family, 1824-1825 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    3 items. Letters to his father on his voyage to New Brunswick, Canada, and on his medical studies in Boston. See Folder 10.
  - Letters to family, 1825-1826 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    5 items. Letters to his father and mother on his voyage to New Orleans with Dr. Henry Little. Recent transcripts of these letters by Rebecca Bernardos. See Folder 11 for a diary of the voyage.
  - Letters to family, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letters to his father, mother and brother Bela from Brunswick, Maine, and Boston.
  - Letters to family, 1828-1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    7 items. Letters to his father, mother, and brother Bela From Burlington, Vermont, where Lincoln was teaching anatomy at the University of Vermont and creating preparations for an anatomical cabinet. His brother Thomas was assisting him in his dissections in 1829. One letter is from Thomas and Benjamin to their brother Bela. The last letter discusses the offer from Nathan R. Smith to teach at the University of Maryland in Baltimore.
  - Letters to family, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2 items. Letters to his father from Baltimore, including a long description of the University of Maryland.
  - Letters to his father, sister, Mary, and brother Thomas, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    10 items. Letters written from Burlington. Includes discussion of the cholera epidemic and a printed notice by the Board of Health (Benjamin Lincoln, Secretary) "To the Inhabitants of the Town of Burlington and its Vicinity," June 25, 1832
  - Letters to family, 1833-1834 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    13 items. Letters to his father and to his brothers, Thomas, Bela, and Edmund on his growing surgical practice, his private students, his ambitious plans for research and writing and for improved medical education, his controversy with Theodore Woodward, his publications, and his health. Includes a printed circular for his pamphlet, Hints on the present state of medical education and the influence of medical schools in New England(1833). The final letter, dated May 23, 1824, from Thomas and Benjamin to Theodore, is about Benjamin returning to Dennysville because of debilitating illness.
  - Letters to Benjamin Lincoln from his father, 1819,1824 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 items.
  - "Journal of a Voyage from Boston to New Orleans", 1825 November 10-1826 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Lincoln was invited by Dr. Henry Little, a botanist, to accompany him on a voyage to Louisiana in order to alleviate Little's suffering from tuberculosis. The journal describes the voyage by ship to Louisiana and travel up the Mississippi to New Orleans. Lincoln described plantations and slavery, the physical, economic, and social conditions, and medicine and public health in New Orleans. The journal includes a separate daily report on the condition of Dr. Little, who died on the voyage home. Folder also includes a transcript of the journal by researcher Rebecca Bernardos.
  - Journal of a Voyage from Eastport, Maine to New Brunswick, 1827 July 20 - 1827 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    55 pages. Lincoln sailed from Eastport, Maine, not far from Dennysville, to St. John, New Brunswick, and visited several other towns in New Brunswick. He carried out a geological survey of New Brunswick, probably encouraged by Parker Cleaveland, geologist and mineralogist at Bowdoin College. The journal includes a variety of other observations, including those on Indians.
  - Miscellany from Bowdoin College, Boston, and Burlington, 1820-1834 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Pencil drawing, presumably of Benjamin Lincoln; itemized receipts for tuition at Bowdoin College, 1820-1823; notes to Lincoln concerning student societies; an engraving of John Doane Wells, M.D. (1799-1830), Professor of Anatomy and Surgery at Bowdoin College, 1822-1830, sent by the Medical Faculty at Bowdoin College to Lincoln in Burlington; commencement admission cards; receipts in Boston; card for the Burlington Assemblies, 1830-1831.
  - Benjamin Lincoln's copy of Catalogue of the Library of the Medical School at Maine of Bowdoin College(Brunswick, Maine: Bowdoin Press, 1830) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Benjamin Lincoln, "Letters addressed to Joseph A. Gallup, M.D." in the Burlington Sentinel, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Four weekly issues, February 28, 1834, March 14, 1834, March 21, 1834, March 28, 1834, containing articles by Lincoln on the poor state of medical education and the ignorance of many physicians. Joseph Gallup, of Woodstock, Vermont, was a leading physician in the state, who had founded a medical college in Woodstock and later resigned from it.
  - Obituary of Benjmin Lincoln in a separate broadside of the Eastport Sentinel, 1835 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - John Wheeler, Historical Sketch of the University of Vermont (1854) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rev. John Wheeler was president of the University of Vermont from 1833 to 1848. On Lincoln, see pp. 27-28.
- Thomas Lincoln and the Lincoln Family, Series II
  - Thomas Lincoln manuscripts on slavery and the Civil War (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Thomas Lincoln sought protection for fugitive slaves.
  - Thomas Lincoln, other manuscripts, 1870 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "Disregard of the feelings of a Marble Statue"; "Anatomy of the Alphabet" (two drafts); letter to "Friend Frothingham," December 9, 1870 on alcohol (two drafts); "Proceedings at the annual Town Meeting"; draft petition to the U.S. House of representatives concerning rocks obstructing passage and commerce in Cobscook Bay, Maine; note on Macauley and current history; and the Constitution of the Burlington Society for the Promotion of Temperance, signed by fourteen people, but neither Benjamin nor Thomas Lincoln.
  - Other items related to Thomas Lincoln, 1834, 1883 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes a small oval color painting Thomas Lincoln; a printed "Memorial. Thomas Lincoln," 1883, and a reprint, sent to Thomas Lincoln, of John Bachman, "An account of some experiments made on the habits of the Vultures inhabiting Carolina, the Turkey Buzzard, and the Carrion Crow, particularly as it regards the extraordinary powers of smelling, usually attributed to them," 1834, on John J. Audubon's experiments, and with pencil corrections.
  - Receipts related to Theodore Lincoln, 1816-1839 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Five items. The last relates to money owed from the University of Vermont.
  - Other family correspondence, 1839, 1844, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Bela Lincoln, Rockingham, Iowa, to Thomas Lincoln, August 7, 1839; Mary O'Brien, Boston, to Mr. and Mrs [Theodore] Lincoln, August 1844; Edmund Lincoln (son of Thomas Lincoln), Kyoto Japan, to Mrs. S. E. Whittier, Lowell, Massachusetts, March 26, 1896. This letter, describing Japan, is on a sheet of paper several feet long folded into an envelope.
  - Lincoln family miscellany, 1832, 1836, and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Receipts and notes.
  - Letters to Mrs. Arthur T. Lincoln, 1927, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Dr. Arthur T. Lincoln was the son of Thomas Lincoln. These two typed letters to Mrs. (Anna?) Lincoln from Frederick F. Black, Searsport, Maine, and from George Cheever Shattuck, Harvard Medical School, relate to the disposition of Benjamin Lincoln's books and papers.
  - Photographs of the Lincoln homestead, Dennysville, Maine (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Four postcards, five photographs, a photograph of unidentified men building a cabin, and a newspaper advertisement for the sale of the Lincoln home.
  - Photographs of members of the Lincoln family (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Photographs of Arthur T. Lincoln, Frederick Bromly Staines, Janet (Jessie) McIndoe Staines (1803-1884), and miniature photographs, presumably of Frederick Bromly Staines as a child. Captions were probably written by Edmund Lincoln's wife, daughter of F. B. Staines and grandaughter of Mrs. Janet Staines. Folder contains comments and genealogical information by a descendent of the Staines family, John Muirhead, in 2017.
  - Photograph albums of the Lincoln family (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Two tiny decorative leather-covered albums, 9 cm x 8 cm. One is stamped Edmund Lincoln, Dennysville.
  - Memorial of the 100th Anniversary of the Settlement of Dennysville, Maine, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Signature of Edmund Lincoln. Includes a brief genealogy of the Lincoln family.
  - Pamphlets, 1839-1922 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Vermont, October 1839
      With signature of Thomas Lincoln, Dennysville, Maine.
    - Thomas Gray, An Elegy in a Country Churchyard. English Classic Series, 1885
      Signature of Edmund Lincoln.
    - Andrew Summers Rowan, How I Carried the Message to Garcia, 1922
      Inscribed by the author to Mrs. Edmund J. S. Lincoln.